Guide to the Winthrop Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Winthrop family papers
1635-1727
GEN MSS 274
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Contains letters from various people, including colonial officials and legislators, to Fitz-John Winthrop, John Winthrop (1588-1649), John Winthrop (1606-1676), and John Winthrop (1681-1747); one letter from Fitz-John Winthrop to Joseph Dudley; and various other documents, including Abraham Pierson's elegy on Theophilus Eaton, and a brief diary by John Winthrop (1606-1676).
Winthrop family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert C. Winthrop, 1897-1898.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Winthrop Family Papers are organized in two series: I. Correspondence and II. Other Papers. The papers span the dates 1635-1720, with the bulk of the material dating from between 1670 and 1710.
Series I, Correspondence, is arranged in three subseries: Incoming Letters, Outgoing Letters, and Third Party Letters. Letters within each subseries are arranged alphabetically by recipient and then by correspondent.
The letters to Fitz-John Winthrop contain information on his particpation in the government of Sir Edmund Andros and his subsequent negotiations in London for the restoration of the colony's charter; Connecticut's border disputes with the colonies of Rhode Island and New York; and Indian conflicts and alliances. Letters to John Winthrop (1588-1649) include two from Roger Williams concerning disputes among Narragansett sachems and fights against the "Dutch Indians;" a June, 1636 letter from Jonathan Brewster discussing the war plans of the Pequots and their distrust of the English; a request for assistance from Lion Gardiner; and letters asking for medical advice and inquiring about conditions of settlement in Connecticut. The correspondence of John Winthrop (1681-1747) contains a request for a description of moose from Cotton Mather and a letter from Thomas Buckingham concerning the founding of the Collegiate School, which is also the subject of a third-party letter from Buckingham to James Fitch.
Series II, Other Papers, is arranged alphabetically by author and includes a "Note of payments disbursed to my son, for the affair of Connecticut" and a travel pass for the Niantic sachem Ninigret, both in the hand of John Winthrop (1588-1649). A contract by John Winthrop (1681-1747) authorizes his agents to purchase a Carbuncle stone from the Indians, if one can be located.
Pequot War, 1636-1638; Connecticut -- Boundaries; Connecticut -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Massachusetts -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; New England -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Territory and Dominion of New-England; United States -- History -- Queen Anne's War, 1702-1713; Allyn, John, -1696; Andros, Edmund, Sir, 1637-1714; Dudley, Joseph, 1647-1720; Eaton, Theophilus, 1590-1658; Gardiner, Lion, 1599-1663; Pierpont, James, 1660-1714; Pierson, Abraham, 1608-1678; Williams, Roger, 1604?-1683; Winthrop, John, 1588-1649; Winthrop, John, 1606-1676; Winthrop, John, 1681-1747; Winthrop family; Collegiate School (New Haven, Conn.)
- Correspondence, 1636-1720; Series I; 54 folders (0.30' linear ft.)
  - INCOMING LETTERS
    - To Fitz-John Winthrop (1638-1707)
      - ALS from John Allyn (d. 1696), 1673 Oct 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Scope and Contents
        Concerning a petition from Long Island; Dutch fleet.
      - ALS from Sir Edmund Andros (1637-1714), Boston, 1687 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Notification that Connecticut is to be "annexd to this Gov.t."
      - ALS from Rev. Gershom Bulkeley (1636-1713), Glastonbury, 1707 Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - ALS from Rev. John Bulkeley (1679-1731), Colchester, 1703 Aug 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - ALS from Rev. Israel Chauncy (1644-1703), Stratford, 1699 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - ALS from John Chester (1656-1711), Wethersfield, 1702 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - ALS from Joseph Dudley (1647-1720), Roxbury, 1702 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - ALS from John Livingston (1680-1720), Albany, 1704 Oct 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Negotiations at Albany.
      - ALS from Robert Livingston (1654-1725), New York City, 1701 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS from James Noyes (1640-1719), 1706 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - ALS from Rev. James Pierpont (1660-1714), New Haven, 1693 Sep 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Encouragement to Winthrop in his negotiations for "our liberties" in London.
      - 2 ALS from Abraham Pierson, Jr. (1646-1707), Killingworth, 1698, 1703 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Dated 1697/8 Feb 25 and 1703 Nov 8.
      - ALS from Gurdon Saltonstall (1666-1724), Stonington, 1698 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        News of the struggle over the Spanish Succession.
      - ALS from Caleb Stanly (1642-1718), Hartford, 1700 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Border dispute with Massachusetts over New Roxbury (Woodstock).
        Postscript dated 1700 Nov 23.
      - ALS from Nathaniel Stanly (1638-1712), Hartford, 1704 Jan 21 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Docketed: "Mr. Stanly about Indians to goe against the enemy."
        Dated 1703/4 Jan 21.
      - ALS from Robert Treat (ca. 1622-1710), Milford, 1702 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - ALS from Daniel Wetherell (1630-1719), New London, 1697 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Rejoicing at Winthrop's return from England.
      - ALS from William Whiting (b. 1659), Hartford, 1700 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - ALS from Wait Still Winthrop (1642-1717), Boston, 1671 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - ALS from Timothy Woodbridge (1656-1732), Hartford, 1707 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - ALS from Samuel Wyllys (1631?-1709), Hartford, 1698 Aug 13 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Concerning disputed Narragansett territory and the mission of a Rhode Island delegate to London.
    - To John Winthrop (1588-1649)
      - ALS from Theophilus Eaton (1590-1658), New Haven, 1647 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Also signed by Stephen Goodyear.
    - To John Winthrop (1606-1676)
      - ALS from John Blackleach (d. 1683), New Haven, 1658 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - ALS from Jonathan Brewster (d. 1659), Plymouth House, 1636 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Concerning the plans of the Pequots and their "mistrust that the English will shortly come agt. them."
      - Petition from Stephen Chester (1639-1705), Hartford, 1670 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        For leave to transport a small load of Indian corn.
      - ALS from Daniel Clarke (1623-1710), Windsor, 1675 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        For medical advice.
      - ALS from Rev. John Davenport (1596-1670), New Haven, 1658 Jan 21 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - ALS from George Fenwick (1603-1657), Saybrook, 1639 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - ALS from Lion Gardiner (1599-1663), Isle of Wight, 1650 Aug 10 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Request for assistance.
      - ALS from William Goodwin (d. 1673), Hadley, 1663 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - ALS from John Haynes (d. 1654), Hartford, 1651 Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - ALS from Rev. Thomas Hooker (1586-1647), [Hartford?], [1636] (Box 1, Folder 32)
        Thanks for his advice.
      - ALS from Edward Hopkins (1599?-1658), London, 1636 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - 5 ALS from Mrs. Hannah Eaton Jones (1632-1707), 1659-75 (Box 1, Folder 34)
        One written before her marriage.
      - ALS from William Jones (1624-1706), New Haven, 1660 Jan 1 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - ALS from Eleazar Kimberly (1639-1709), Hartford, 1698 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - ALS from William Leete (1612 or 13-1683), Guilford, 1661 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - ALS from Richard Lord (1611 or 12-1662), New Haven, 1653 Jul 14 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - ALS from John Mason (1600-1672), Norwich, 1664 Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - ALS from John Tinker (d. 1662), New London, 1659 [Aug] 29 (Box 1, Folder 40)
        Concerning settling with his family and operating a sawmill.
      - 2 ALS from Roger Williams (1604?-1683); Nar[ragansett], Providence, [1649], 1669 (Box 1, Folder 41)
        1649 letter concerns disputes among various sachems and fighting with the "Dutch Indians."
        Dated 1649 Aug 25 and 1669 Aug 19.
      - ALS from David Yale (1614-1690), London, 1656 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - 4 ALS from Thomas Yale (d. 1683), 1659-72 (Box 1, Folder 43)
        Family news; medical advice sought.
    - To John Winthrop (1681-1747)
      - ALS from Eliphalet Adams (1677-1753), New London, 1717 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - ALS from Rev. Thomas Buckingham (1646-1709), Saybrook, 1701 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 45)
        Concerning the founding of the Collegiate School (later Yale).
      - ALS from Richard Edwards (1647-1718), Hartford, 1714 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - ALS from Rev. Dr. Cotton Mather (1663-1728), Boston, 1714 [Mar?] 30 (Box 1, Folder 47)
        Requesting a description of moose [for the Royal Society?].
      - ALS from Rev. John Walton (1694-1764), Yale College, 1720 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 48)
        Offers a copy of his elegy for Governor [Joseph] Dudley.
  - OUTGOING LETTERS
    - From Fitz-John Winthrop (1638-1707)
      - Copy of letter to Gov. Joseph Dudley (1647-1720), New London, 1704 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 49)
        Concerning the "unreasonable" request for men and supplies to fight the French and Indians in Hampshire; counteroffer of two hundred men. Remonstrates against Dudley's complaint to the Crown.
  - THIRD PARTY LETTERS
    - Buckingham, Rev. Thomas (1646-1709)
      - ALS to Major James Fitch (1649-1727), 1702 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 50)
        On progress of the Collegiate School (later Yale College).
      - ALS to Rev. Gurdon Saltonstall (1666-1724), 1702 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 51)
        For help from the Governor.
    - Gold, Nathan (1663?-1723). ALS to "Honored Sir", Fairfield, 1703 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Rejecting a request that the Governor travel [to London?].
      Leaf addressed to "The Hon.ble Robert Treat, Governor" but letter possibly not to him.
      Docketed: "their opinion upon reading the Agents letter."
      Also signed by Joseph Curtiss and Peter Burr.
    - Stanton, Thomas (1638-1718). ALS to Gov. Simon Bradstreet (1603-1697), Stonington, 1692 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Docketed: "A letter about the Mortgage of the Narragansett Country." Concerns boundary dispute.
      Also signed by his four brothers.
    - Stow, Rev. Samuel (1622-1704). ALS to Wait Winthrop (1642-1717), Middletown, 1692 Aug 4 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Other Papers, 1635-1727; Series II; 9 folders (0.10' linear ft.)
  - Pierson, Abraham (d. 1678). Elegy on Theophilus Eaton (1590-1658), [Branford?] (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Stow, Rev. Samuel (1622-1704). Scheme of Godliness or of the true religion, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Sent to Gov. Fitz-John Winthrop.
  - Talcott, Joseph (1669-1741). Certificate to certain official signatures, Hartford, 1727 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Winthrop, John (1588-1649)
    - Note of payments disbursed for my son, for the affair of Connecticut, [1635?] (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Pass for Ninigret to go to Boston, [1646 Jan 14?] (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Winthrop, John (1606-1676)
    - Diary of journey from Boston to Saybrook, and return, 1645 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 60)
      Partly in Latin.
    - Copies, in his hand, of the will and Letter of Administration of Gov. Theophilus Eaton (1590-1658), [ca. 1656-57] (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Resignation of governorship, 1675 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Winthrop, John (1681-1747)
    - Agreement with J. Smith and J. Gallup, Plainfield, 1716 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      Advancing Smith and Gallup funds to purchase the "Carbuncle and so much talkt of Shining Stone" from the Indians.
      Docket by Winthrop noting that the funds were all returned to him.